Finding Aid for Margie J. Van Meter papers, 1968-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Margie J. Van Meter papers 1968-1986
Van Meter, Margie J.
1.5 linear feet
2011076 Aa
Margie J. Van Meter was among the first clinical nurse specialists at the University of Michigan. Her papers document her training as a clinical nurse specialist at the University of Michigan's School of Nursing and the early years of her nursing career in the University of Michigan Health System. The collection contains Van Meter's daily journals (4 spiral notebooks), covering the years between 1970 and 1972. Various administrative materials and educational material are included in the papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was received in 2002 (donor no. 9274 ).
No further additions are expected.
Restricted access in part; see access restrictions on following page.
The RECORD GROUP record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Patient/Client Records -- Boxes 2
Margie J. Van Meter was a Clinical Nursing Specialist at the University of Michigan Hospital following her graduation from the School of Nursing graduate program in 1970. She worked primarily on the 9 West floor of the University Hospital, as well as in the hospital's pain clinic. Van Meter was also the Coordinator of Nursing Quality, and was the Recording Secretary for the Nursing Honorary Society, Sigma Rho.
Van Meter later became involved with the Haiti Nursing Foundation, an organization that provides financial support to the school of nursing at Faculté des Sciences Infirmières [de Léogâne] l'Université Episcopale d'Haïti, as well as funding for various projects to improve nursing in Haiti. She was the recipient of the Friend of Nursing Award in 2009 from the University of Michigan School of Nursing.
The Margie J. Van Meter Papers are divided into three series relating to her education and work as a clinical nursing specialist: Administrative, Clinical Nursing Specialist records, School of Nursing, Patient Logs and Records.
Subjects:
Van Meter, Margie J., 1937-; Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nurse practitioners.; University of Michigan. Medical-Surgical Nursing Area.; University of Michigan. Hospital.
- Clinical Nursing Specialist records
  The Clinical Nursing Specialist records contain records from Van Meter's time on the 9 West floor of the University of Michigan Hospital, as well as papers from an MBO (Management by Objectives) workshop. Two bound packets distributed at Clinical Nursing Specialist (CNS) symposiums reflect early meetings and organization of Clinical Nursing Specialists from 1974 and 1975.
  - Administrative (Box 1)
    - 9 West, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
    - MBO (Management by Objectives) Workshop, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Meeting/Staff Notes, 1971-1978 (Box 1)
    - Position Description (CNS, Clinical Nursing Specialist), 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Clinical Nursing Specialist Symposium, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Clinical Nursing Specialist Symposium, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1978, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Forms (Box 1)
  - Self Evaluations, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
- School of Nursing
  The School of Nursing series contains van Meter's notes from medical-surgical seminars, as well as from other classes and workshops between 1968 and 1970. Term papers done by Van Meter are included.
  - Class and Workshop Notes, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Medical-Surgical Seminars
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Term Papers, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
- Patient Records and Logs
  The series Patient Records and Logs is restricted due to the presence of name identifiable patient information. These records consist of four spiral-bound notebooks containing Van Meter's daily notes, remarks, reflections on CNS care and practices, and patient observations from 1970 to 1972, as well as a smaller notebook with similar contents. Patient Files contains similar materials, the personal medical records of those patients treated by Van Meter at the University of Michigan Hospital. These records include patient profiles, nursing assessments, and updates on patient conditions.
  - Patient Logs, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
    [CR Restricted until July 1, 2074 ]
  - Patient Records, 1970-1974, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Patient Files Discharged, 1971 (Box 2)